Finding Aid for the Zamin Ki Dost Papers LSC.0740
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zamin Ki Dost papers
1930-1960
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zamin Ki Dost, 1866-1947
LSC.0740
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Zamin Ki Dost (1866-1947) was a medical missionary in India and lectured throughout the U.S. for Armenian Relief before settling in Los Angeles to teach philosophy and write stories and poems. The collection consists of literary manuscripts, including a manuscript biography by Zamin Ki Dost's disciple, Mattaline G. Crabtree, manuscripts of Dost's mystical teachings interpreted by Crabtree, correspondence between Lawrence Clark Powell and Crabtree, and ephemera.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9936493723606533
Biography
Born Willimina Leonora Armstrong in Nebraska in 1866 and educated in Philadelphia, Zamin Ki Dost went to India in 1887 as a medical missionary; her experience furnished the material for her book, Incense of sandalwood; near the end of the century she lectured throughout the U.S. for Armenian Relief; in 1901 settled in Los Angeles, a semi-invalid from a broken spine, teaching philosophy from her home and writing stories and poems; published Son of power (1920), stories of India written under the pseudonym Zamin Ki Dost and in collaboration with Will Levington Comfort; she died in 1947.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of literary manuscripts, including a manuscript biography by Zamin Ki Dost's disciple, Mattaline G. Crabtree, manuscripts of Dost's mystical teachings interpreted by Crabtree, correspondence between Lawrence Clark Powell and Crabtree, and ephemera.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Manuscripts.
Correspondence with Dr. Lawrence Clark Powell & ephemera.
Additional Physical Form Available
A copy of the original version of this online finding aid is available at the UCLA Department of Special Collections for in-house consultation and may be obtained for a fee. Please contact:
Public Services Division
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Room A1713, Charles E. Young Research Library
Box 951575
Los Angeles, CA 90095-1575
Telephone: 310/825-4988 (10:00 a.m. - 4:45 p.m., Pacific Time)
Email: spec-coll@library.ucla.edu
Women mystics -- United States -- Archives.; Women poets, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Women authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Powell, Lawrence Clark -- Correspondence; Crabtree, Mattaline G; Zamin Ki Dost, 1866-1947
- Incense of Sandalwood. Los Angeles, California: Baumgarten Publishing Company, 1904.
  - Copy 1, April 20, 1940. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Holograph inscription in ink, Dear Gertrude..., signed, W.L.A., 2105 Oak Glen Place, Los Angeles, California.
  - Copy 2., June 5, 1938. (Box 1)
    Holograph inscription in ink to Carey McWilliams.
- Essential Things to Know and Do, by the Noor Zhan. Compiled by Her Chela. Los Angeles, California: New Age Publishing Company, 1957. (Box 1)
- Pamphlet., 37pp. (Box 1)
- Teachings of the Noor Zhan (Answers to Questions) Compiled by Her Chela. n.p., n.d. (Box 1)
  Typescript. 158pp. In brown clip-binder.
- 4 manuscripts:
  - Phenomena of the Spheres (Flying Saucers) Dictated by the Noor Zhan. n.p., August 10, 1952.; Typescript (carbon) title in holograph. 17 leaves. (Box 1)
  - Three Messages from the Noor Zhan to her Children of the Light. n.p., July-August 1958.; Typescript (carbon) title and closing inscription in holograph. 4 leaves. (Box 1)
  - Essential Things to Know and Do, by the Noor Zham. n.p., Typescript (mimeograph copy). 23 leaves. Manila covers. (Box 1)
    Front cover with holograph title and inscription: Presented to Dr. Lawrence Clark Powell and family with love, by M.G.C.
  - Teachings Concerning Business Practices in the New Era. n.p., n.d.; Typescript (mimeograph copy). 2 leaves. (Box 1)
    All the manuscripts end with ...The Noor Zhan has spoken through the hand of her Chela.
- The Noor Zhan, Compiled by Her Chela. [Copy 2] n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon). 768pp. In blue paper box. (Box 1)
  9 parts stapled in individual covers, each labeled in holograph. Also included is a 7pp. table of contents. Biography of Willimina L. Armstrong.
- Correspondence and ephemera re Willimina L. Armstrong. Letters to Dr. Lawrence Clark Powell from Martha., 41 letters: 25 pieces ephemera. (Box 3)
- A Basket of Whatnot. n.p., n.d.; Typescript. Some pagination and correction in holograph. 275 leaves. In brown and buff box with title and some notations in holograph. (Box 2)
  1 or 2-page poems of essays, each identified as being by Miss Armstrong.
- India's Gates. n.p., Typescript.ca. 400pp. (leaves) In maroon box, with title and some holograph notations on side label. (Box 2)
  40 individual stories, each clipped separately; pages unnumbered.
- Jeopardies of Passion. n.p., n.d.; Typescript.ca. 300 leaves. In maroon box, with title and some holograph notations on side label. (Box 3)
  23 individual stories, each clipped separately; pages unnumbered.
- Miscellaneous manuscripts. n.p., n.d.; Typescripts. 3 pieces. (Box 3)
  Included are several leaves of biographic data re Miss Armstrong.